From untitled episode, Idaho Budget Committee introduces new health and welfare budget with additional cuts.
New state budget intended to replace budget that Idaho Senate rejected on March 12th by Clark Corbin, March 19th, 2026, 5.08 p.m.
The exterior of the Idaho exterior of the of the Idaho Statehouse, as seen on March 16th, 2026, in Boise for the Idaho capital sun.
The Idaho Legislature's Budget Committee introduced a new health and human services budget Thursday that includes $21 million in additional budget cuts to Medicaid disability services.
Get the morning headlines. The new budget replaces Senate Bill 375, the original fiscal year 2027 health and human services maintenance of operations budget, which the Idaho Senate killed on March 12th.
Senators killed the original budget following an impassioned debate from Sen. Jim Guthrie McCammon.
The new health and human services budget introduced Thursday includes one change from the original budget the Senate killed.
The new budget reduces funding by an additional $21 million in connection with House Bill 863.
House Bill 863 is a separate bill that would cut provider rates for residential habilitation programs.
That bill advanced out of the Senate Health and Welfare Committee on Wednesday, the Idaho capital sun previously reported.
Reducing funding for the services will cause the state to miss out on an additional $44 million in federal funds, according to state budget documents.
That brings the total cost of the funding reduction to $65 million after the lost federal funds are calculated.
The fiscal year 2027 health and human services maintenance budget includes funding for the Idaho Department of Health and Welfare and the Independent Living Council.
Idaho Republicans governor have pushed for state budget cuts throughout 2026 session.
Budget cuts have been the defining and some of the most controversial elements of the 2026 legislative session.
Governor Brad Little and the Idaho legislature are cutting budgets for most state agencies.
639 engaged.